<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The preachers plea or, A short declaration, touching the sad condition of our clergy, in relation to the smalnesse of their maintenance, throughout the kingdome. / By William Typing. Esq;</title>
            <author>Tipping, William, 1598-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3566</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1111_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1965</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860710</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860710</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112835</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95489)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112835)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 163:E1111[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The preachers plea or, A short declaration, touching the sad condition of our clergy, in relation to the smalnesse of their maintenance, throughout the kingdome. / By William Typing. Esq;</title>
                  <author>Tipping, William, 1598-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 23, 26-27, 30-31, 34-35, 38-39, 43-22 [i.e. 44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Wilson, for Christopher Meredith, at the signe of the Crane in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Numerous errors in pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Salaries, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112835:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Preachers Plea: OR, A ſhort Declaration, touching the ſad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Clergy, in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ſmalneſſe of their maintenance, throughout the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM TYPING. <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by W. WILSON, for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith,</hi> at the Signe of the Crane in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:112835:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112835:2"/>
            <head>THE Preachers Plea.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E live in doubtfull times; I feare a Cloud of bloud hangs over us, as a ſtreame of bloud hath already ran round about us. Me thinkes the frame of our ſpirits, preſage it; for wee have had various diſpenſations of Gods dealings with us. Firſt, ſhewers of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then gleams of mercy ſcattered in the Land; yet the ſame temper lies ſtill brooding</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:112835:3"/>
            <p> on our hearts. Puniſhments will not awaken us, bleſſings cannot melt us. <hi>Perdidimus utilitatem calamitatis noſtrae, miſeri facti ſumus, &amp; peſſimi permanemus.</hi> What ſhould God doe with ſuch a ſinfull people? We have been, and will continue a ſtubborne ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. Is it not ſtrange that in ſuch a gratious ſeaſon as this, when ſuch an inundatlon of loving kindneſſe have bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in upon us from the Lord, and hee hath holpen us ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly in our pinching ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, farre beyond what we could expect, or hope for. Yea, that now, whilſt his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are hot, and reaking in our memories, the worke of our God ſhould ſo ſticke in our hands, and our begun Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation move, like <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:112835:3"/>Chariots when the Wheelos were off, with ſuch a dull and ſlow progreſſion. The Lord grant our Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions prove not reſervations to greater judgements. I feare, leſt what <hi>Salvianus</hi> ſighed our againſt another people, ſhould prove our fatall doome. <hi>Sopor infunditur ut perditio ſubſequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> The Truth is, nothing, gives beauty and gloſſe to our cauſe, but our glorious victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Take us abſtracted from our happy ſucceſſes, (and they are none of ours) and what miſerable Chriſtians ſhall wee appeare. Was there ever any Chriſtian Nation under hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that after ſo many Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants to reforme, ſo many cleare demonſtrations from heaven, of Gods acceptance of our Covenants, have yet
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112835:4"/>abounded in ſo many and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Sects, Schiſmes, Hereſies, Blaſphemies, and that with ſo high a hand, and in ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controlable a way, as this out Nation. Adde to this, what a world of time hath beene crumbled away in debate on Church-government; yet how little Progreſſe is made therin? How farre are we at this day, from an eſtabliſhment thereof throughout the Kingdome? Something indeed hath been concluded on by our Worthy Patriots, in order to the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian way: but what is a branch to the Tree; what is this to the ſetling of the whole body, and Bulke of a Church-government, and of Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline in the Realme; for want where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſinne abounds, and many
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112835:4"/>fearefull Tranſgreſſions goe unpuniſhed. And how doth our unhappy Church (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this good hand of God upon us) lie ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, afflicted, diſgraced, impoveriſhed, cloathed with her old Ragges, fed with her old maintenance, ſerved with her old Chaplaines, having neither meanes nor Miniſters ſerviceable for any uſe almoſt, but to ſtand as Monuments of her ſhame. The conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof hath (I muſt confeſſe) very often, much ſadded my heart; and at this time preſt mee to this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. Surely, what ever mens hearts may deſire, their eyes ſhal never ſee able Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in our Church, untill there be able maintenance to encourage them: For Worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112835:5"/>will not bee got without wages, nor will the wages bee any invitation to the worke, if it be ſet forth as formerly, in a baſe and deſpicable proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It's true indeed, wee have formerly had to the ſcorne of our Church and Kingdom, and to the undoing of thouſands of ſoules, the loweſt of the people for the ſerviee of Gods houſe. Ignorant &amp; contemptible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons through the corruption of this worſer age, have beene advanced to the moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable calling the world could yeeld. And from whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded this iniquity? why ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous meanes uſhered in ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous men: <hi>ad tenuitatem be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiorum, ſequebatur igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia ſacerdotum.</hi> Poverty brought in ignorance into the Church, &amp; ignorance brought
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112835:5"/>in ſcorne. For what eve mens integrity and parts may be, a torne coate ſeldome findes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence or regard amonſt the common ſort of people; who for the moſt part meaſure out their reſpect to their Paſtors, not according to their inward abilites, but according to their outward garbe and greatneſſe. The Parliaments frame the 27. of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. (who gave a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way impropriations from the Church, or did that which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to the ſame) to this day, have (I feare) ſomething to anſwer for, that in ſo large a tract of time, have found out no expedient, whereby to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Patrimony of the Church into a competency.</p>
            <p>It was but reaſon when they had taken away the joynture of the Church, to aſſigne ſome
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112835:6"/>livelihood to maintaine her. Truly want amongſt all condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men, is a very melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly thing: but it muſt needs lie neareſt the heart of a labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Paſtor, becauſe over and beſides his owne perſonall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, the honour of God is concerned therein. For let rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſpeake, is it not ſinne and ſhame, that the ſervants of the moſt high God, who in a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar manner draw nigh to him in the ſervice of his Church, ſhould be ſo courſly entertain'd, as to have little better then <hi>Daniels</hi> dainties, to preſerve them, or live like poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> with the crums that fall from rich mens Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. Certainely the ſlighting of an Embaſſadour reflects up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Soveraigne, and the Mr. Takes himſelfe to be diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112835:6"/>when his ſervant is abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or held in a baſe eſteeme, and can we reaſonably imagine the Lord of Heaven &amp; Earth, who, when hee might juſtly have made us the reproach of all Nations for our ſinnes, hath now ſo gloriouſly exalted us in the ſight of men, will not take it unkindly, yea in high indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, if after all our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in a bleſſed Reformation we ſhould looke on his Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours with a regardleſſe eye? but I hope better things. I truſt the time is comming, and will haſten on, when burning and ſhining lamps ſhall bee ſet up in every corner of the Land, and oyle enough provided to keepe them flaming. But till the ſecond be brought to paſs, I expect not the firſt, until there bee a tolerable ſubſiſtence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112835:7"/>in every Pariſh, it's im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible there ſhould be (what wee have ſo long expected) a conſtant faithfull preaching Miniſtery throughout the Kingdome. Men may fancie to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves what they pleaſe, talke of Elders, debate on go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; but beleeve it, theſe things will never be brought into act &amp; exerciſe, ſo as God ſhall bee glorified, and the people edified thereby, till this be done. This is the hinge on which all muſt turn. I know not how the iniquity of the times have brought it about, but ſo it is, God is not in cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite among Chriſtians as in dayes of olde. Nor hath his ſervants and ſervice <hi>(Pudet haec dici potuiſſe)</hi> that reverend regard, which former age hath given them.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:112835:7"/>
            <p> Time was when men of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and high Parentage, cheerfully devoted themſelves to the ſervice of the Church, as <hi>Hilary, Eaſill, Fulgentius,</hi> &amp; divers others, though Nobly borne, yet thought it there higher honour to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves inſtrumental to the work of the Goſpell. But alas as the meanes and fortunes of the Church grew low, ſo devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and affection to the ſervice thereof declined with them, &amp; the encouragements to lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning being taken away, mens ſpirits were ſoone becalmed toward that way. I hope, I ſhal not here be offenſive to any in ſpeaking for thoſe, who bluſh to ſpeake for themſelves, and in pleading for due honour to a deſpiſed calling.</p>
            <p>I think it were a noble Chriſtian
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112835:8"/>pollicy; and now is the golden opportunity, to ſet forth good preferment for this high and honourable imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that thereby men of the worthieſt parts, and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite endowments of nature and learning, might be invited thereunto. The want whereof hath beene the cauſe that ſuch as have been of the darkeſt and dulleſt conſtitutions, and to whom nature hath been, ſome way or other an unkinde Step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, and have bin thought fit for nothing elſe, have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been condemned to this worke. When as men of the moſt refined wits and greateſt hopes have been ſetled by their parents and guardians, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vocations, as in eſpeciall the Law, that being looked on as a ſtep to honour and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112835:8"/>but this reputed as a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right way to beggery. Some there are, but I beleeve they are ſuch as partake more of the Serpent then of the Dove, who upon this chaunge of Church-government, ſeeme to be very anxious, leſt the Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall power ſhould only put on a new coate, as it weare, and faſhion, and retain his former pride and ſtatelineſſe, under the forme of the Presbytery. Therefore cry out, keep them poore to reſtraine their pride, raiſe not the winds that ſhould fill their ſailes, for meanes will but make them ſwell.</p>
            <p>Thus wanton witts fall heavily upon the Miniſters of the GOSPELL in theſe cenſorious times, and prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge them for their pride whereas God knowes for the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112835:9"/>preſent they ſtand in that deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picable condition in divers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that they ſcarce have cloaths to cover them. Yet I dare be bold to ſay, never were there any times ſince the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Goſpell in this Kingdome, wherein the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Land have beene more engaged to their Paſtors (I relate more ſpecially to this Citie) for their prayers, pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in preaching, &amp; all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Chriſtian love and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety then in theſe our dayes. What ever unkinde blaſts they lye under, ſure I am, the right hand of the Lord hath done gloriouſly for us by their meanes, theſe are the Doves of the valley, which have brought in more Victories by their cryes and teares to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, then all our armies by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112835:9"/>their ſtrength, yet theſe are the men (as ſome calumniate) whom no bonds are like to hold, no bounds to reſtraine, unleſſe they bee held in with bit and bridle. But let men of this temper and condition ſpeake as ſmoothly as they pleaſe, &amp; bring the moſt plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible arguments their wits can deviſe, to cover their naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hearts withal: yet ſhall I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver beleeve hee loves a godly Miniſter that pleads to keepe him low, or that hee is ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good that ſwells at good mens greatneſſe. If the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpell be good, its neceſſary they ſhould be great, I meane that their maintenance be raiſed to ſuch an ample pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, as ſhould not onely ſhelter them from ſcorne, but adorne their Callings. The
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112835:10"/>Prieſts and Levites under the Law, as they drew nigheſt to God in regard of Office, and were next to his preſence, in regard of place (for they were by Gods expreſſe command to pitch their Tents round about the Tabernacle) ſo alſo was the Lord pleaſed to make ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable proviſion for them, by aſſigning the tenths and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liberal allowance for their ſupport. Now whether the tenths of all mens profits, do in theſe times, as under the law, in duty appertaine to the Miniſters of the Goſpell, I intend not here to diſcuſſe. But ſure I am, maintenance is their right, and the diſpenſers of the Goſpell are not inferiour to the Miniſters of the Law, therefore Religion and reaſon ſuggeſts, they ſhould have that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112835:10"/>proportion or a better part, at leaſt a ſufficiency to buy bookes, keep Hoſpitality, and live like Miniſters in a reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able condition.</p>
            <p>It was well with Gods Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, when they were at Gods finding, as under the Law; but we, alas, have ſtrait Bowels, and cloſe hands, and God knowes, there is too much of ſelfe in all our boſomes; (&amp; that which checks our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs, I feare in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular is) we have too much of their Bread in our owne poſſeſſions. I beſeech thoſe whom this great buſineſſe doth moſt properly concerne, to lay their hands upon their hearts, and ſeriouſly conſider and conſult, which way this Epidemicall ſickneſſe in the Church may bee removed. It
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112835:11"/>would make a mans heart bleed, to ſee how many drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ignorant, ſuperſtitious, Prophane Miniſters, are crept into every corner of the land, more abundantly, (I think) in <hi>Oxford-ſhire,</hi> than in any County againe in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: where (to the aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of this miſerie) they are in divers places on a ſuddaine turned conſtant Preachers, which ſeldome or never preached before; but yet continue Drunkards ſtill. For the turne of the times hath frighted them into a forme of Preaching, to ſave their livings; but are as ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous as ever in their lives: and ſurely till the baſeneſſe and poverty of the proviſion ſet out for them be reformed, this miſchiefe will not be cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112835:11"/>of redreſſe. For you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not caſt unworthy Teachers out of the Church, untill you have introduced more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſubſiſtance into the <hi>Church;</hi> if you doe, you may locke up the Church doores; for what men of any gifts will ſupply the cures? It is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>puted that there are in the Kingdom nine thouſand two hundred Pariſh Churches, and upward, whereof neare foure thouſand are impropriate Churches. Beſides many Parſonages are poore, and unable to give en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment to a godly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent teacher, as being abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſpoyled under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of long Leaſes, and rate Tithes, in ſtead of Tithes in kinde. In ſome places, ten pound, eight pound, ſix pound, five pound ten ſhillings, <hi>per
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112835:12"/>annum,</hi> is the Paſtors enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment for himſelfe and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. This is better known in the Countrey, then it is here laid to heart. Yea in this famous City, which God hath even miraculouſly preſerved from the common calamity, as a little <hi>Zoar</hi> to hide his righteous <hi>Lots</hi> in; how have we repayed the loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Lord? There are at this preſent (as I am very credibly informed) two and thirty Pariſh Churches in this City, utterly deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of any Paſtors, to break the bread of life to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and this defect is given in, chiefely to ariſe from the ſcant and tenaceous ſubſiſtence which the places yeeld to the reſpective Miniſters thereof. To inſtance in <hi>Buttolph</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſgate,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112835:12"/>where the allowance for the Miniſter is but 16. l. <hi>per annum</hi> (ſaving 7. l. more, or thereabouts, given by <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, (very hardly paid,) and did not the vicinity of of other Churches in this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous City, hold forth ſome eaſe and accommodation to ſupply the want of the deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Churches aforeſaid, the Inhabitants there muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily have been reduced into as ſad a ſtrait as thoſe in the Countrey, who through the perſecution of theſe times have loſt their Teachers.</p>
            <p>Now if things muſt ſtand at this ſtay, what will become of us, and where ſhall wee ſee the fruit of our Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Wee give God good words with our mouthes, but if wee acknowledge him our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112835:13"/>Lord, where is his honour? Oh that we would ſit downe a while, and reflect into our ſelves, forget our ſwelling thoughts, and look a little backe to the dayes of our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity. How did our Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes beat three yeares ſince, what Prayers, and Cries, and Teares did wee then ſend up to heaven, in that our low condition? and how did we then lift up our hands and hearts to the moſt high God, and ſweare, and ingage, that we would endeavour a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, as in Religion, ſo in Diſcipline and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo: but what Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in Religion and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, are we or our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities like to joy in, if no effectuall care or courſe ſhould
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112835:13"/>be taken, (as yet I humbly conceive it is not) for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of godlineſſe, and godly Preachers throughout the Kingdome. But we thinks I heare ſome reply, there is no cauſe of this complaint, for the Honourable houſes of Parliament have already made proviſion for augmentation of ſmall livings out of Deane and Chapter Lands, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent Impropriations. To this I humbly anſwer, that how plauſible ſoever this proviſion may ſeeme at firſt ſight, yet I ſuppoſe it will ſtand at a great diſtance from a full ſupply. For the firſt of theſe, namely Dean and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Lands: Theſe are in part already diſpoſed of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way: as for inſtance, in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112835:14"/>the County of <hi>Oxon,</hi> the Deane and Chapter in <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> is comprehended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Articles for <hi>Oxford:</hi> And the Deane and Chapter at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and that at <hi>Windſor,</hi> proviſion is made out of them ſtill, (as I am credibly informed) for divers perſons, that were ſetled in thoſe houſes, and had not ſlewed any diſaffection to the Cauſe. And this being agreeable to common equity and juſtice, I beleeve the ſame rule is obſerved in all other ſuch places alſo. So that the Deane and Chapter Lands are not all diſpoſed of, at leaſt for the preſent, to the ſaid intended uſe.</p>
            <p>Beſides all this, divers Counties there are in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112835:14"/>Kingdome, which have no Deane and Chapter peculiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belonging to them: and where there are ſome ſmall Proportions of theſe Lands, lying ſcattered in ſeverall Counties, this is no way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable to ſo great a want. Now for Impropriations, ſince the benefit that ſhall ariſe from them to this uſe, muſt iſſue onely from thoſe that are ſetled in the hands of Delinquents, it cannot bee conceived, that theſe ſhould hold forth any great benefit or ſuccour to the Church: moſt of your Impropriations doubtleſſe being in the hands of Colledges, and Hoſpitalls or of ſuch perſons as are well-affected to the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>But that which is alſo a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112835:15"/>maine obſtruction and <hi>Remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> to this great Worke, is, (let it bee ſuppoſed, but not granted) that theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions before ſpecified, could poſſibly raiſe the maintenance of the Church to ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Competencie: yet how ſhall the Remedy bee applyed? how, or by what meanes ſhall it bee transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to thoſe that want it? Will you ſuffer Malignant Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes to lye deſtitute of the meanes of their ſalvation, till they feele their miſery, and finde hearts to complaine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove. Or can you imagine, that ſuch Pariſhes, as have for this twenty, thirty, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares together been nuſled up under an unpreaching Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, will all on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112835:15"/>hunt about from one County to another for Dean and Chapter Lands; or make inquiſition after Delinquent Impropriations, that out of them, or either of them, they may extract ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable ſuſtenance for a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſter? Surely, you may as well ſuppoſe the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of a Church may hap to walke, or that dead bones will ſtirre, or that a man in a ſwoone will call for a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall, as conceive, that men of unregenerate hearts, and that are alienated from the life of grace, through the ignorance that is in them, will ever ſeek out for an able and ſufficient Paſtor, and meanes for his ſupport. Leave ſuch poore ſoules to the unhappy guidance of their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112835:16"/>owne corrupt hearts, and doe nothing for them, till themſelves complaine, and then the Lord have mercy on them. Where Viſion failes the people muſt needs periſh; but what will follow? ſurely it will fall heavie ſomewhere in the end. Oh thinke of this, I beſeech you, (I relate to thoſe whom this great buſines doth moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly concerne) for plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is moſt becoming in the Cauſe of God) thinke of this, whilſt the LORD vouchſafes an opportunity in your hands for th eredreſſe hereof, Yee cannot now ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Labourers in Chriſts Vineyard to be meanly provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for upon ſo cheap tearms as formerly: For theſe things now cry ſo much lowder in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112835:16"/>the eares of God, by how much your ingagements have been deeper to reform them. Alas, doe not your hearts yearne, and the bowels of your compaſſions role within you, when you, living here by an eſpeciall providence, under the droppings of heaven, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the plentifull Preaching of the Word, do underſtand of the ſoule-afflictions of your brethren in your reſpective Counties? How would they rejoyce in ſome places to glean after your Harveſt? to heare one of thoſe Sermons once in a moneth, which you have, or might partake of, (if your leaſure would permit) every day. The Lord direct your ſpirits that yee may no leſſe ſpeedily than carefully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:112835:17"/>that due honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bee given to them that labour in the Word and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: and that yee may not expoſe poore ſenſeleſſe ſoules to everlaſting ruine, by ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpending your helpe, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of them to ſeek for that which they care not to finde; nay, which they extreamly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline, to wit the means of their ſalvation; but that you would be pleaſed rather to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Committees of each Countie, to look into the ſtate of the Miniſtery, and to certifie the defects in that particular.</p>
            <p>And for the remedy of this great ſickneſſein the Land, the poverty of the Clergy; I think there cannot bee a more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall expedient than the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:112835:17"/>in of Impropriations. I doubt not, but every man who hath any thing of Chriſt in him, his hand will bee inlarged, and heart inflam'd to ſo worthy a worke.</p>
            <p>And in truth, Free-willl Offerings are the moſt accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Sacrifices to God. Where we give what is our owne, and coſts us ſomething, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is more pleaſing to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, then where wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow that wherein we have no intereſt, farther forth than as the iniquity of the times doth caſt it into our hands, though that may come in to help alſo.</p>
            <p>Adde to this, that ſome comfort and incouragement would ariſe to the dejected ſpirits of the poore Clergie in divers parts of the Kingdome;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112835:18"/>if ſuch Vicarages and Parſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as are exceeding ſmall, as fifty pound <hi>per annum,</hi> or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, might bee freed in theſe pinching times, from having any Contributions or Quarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings laid upon them. And here (although it may ſeeme a digreſſion from the buſineſſe in hand) yet I cannot but vent my troubled thoughts for the ſpirituall bondage and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this whole Nation in all the parts thereof, groans under in theſe diſtempered times, for want of that care and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhould bee had, to inſtruct the ignorant in the maine grounds and principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Catechiſing is now growne almoſt quite out of uſe amongſt us. Hence it is, ſo many ſtrange, abhorred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:112835:18"/>of opinions have lately ſprung up in divers quarters of the Land; for mens fancies are buſie things, and will ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on work where they are not wrought on; and where the underſtanding is left like fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ground until'd, and hath no ſeeds of Gods word caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, no marvaile if the Divell ſow his tares O that the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſes of Parliament would bee pleaſed to take this into their deep &amp; ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, that ſome Directory for Catechiſing may ſpeedily bee ſent into all Churches of the Kingdome, leſt in the roome of formality and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, (for the purging out whereof ſuch care is taken) Atheiſme and palpable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe creepe not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112835:19"/>them. I ſay no more, hee that is wiſe will ponder theſe things, and the man of underſtanding will lay them to heart.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
